A Guide to the Atcheson L. Hench Autograph Collection
Special Collections, University of Virginia Library
- Series II: Collection of Modern Autographs
  - 1936 January 29 Joseph Wood Krutch (1893-1970), The Nation, to J. John Munson, discusses his biography of Edgar Allan Poe in detail including his motivation in writing it, his use of a biographical essay approach rather than the normal biographical approach, and the value of psychoanalysis applied to a biographical and literary study of Poe, 2 typewritten pages on 2 l. (6435) (Box-folder 9:68)
  - [1832] July 5 Richard Lander (1804-1834) to John Astley, writes of plans for a voyage on the Quorra, a British steam ship owned by the Birkenhead firm of shipbuilders, fitted out in Liverpool at John Laird's Boiler Yard, and under the orders of R. Sanders & Co., his brother, MacGregor Laird, used the ship for a commercial expedition to the River Niger in 1832, 1833, and 1834; 2 pages on 1 l., with an engraving of Richard Lander (6435-n) (Box-folder 9:69)
  - 1834 December 2 John Lander (1807-1839) to John Astley, reports that his family is doing well and refers to the engraving of Richard Lander that Charles Turner, "the eminent mezzotint engraver" will do based on the portrait by Mr. Brockden, if John Lander can secure fifty subscriptions for it. Lander also mentions having a miniature sketch of a statue of Richard Lander to be erected in Truro, Cornwall. (6435-n) (Box-folder 9:70)
  - 1918 July 19 Franklin K. Lane (1864-1921), Secretary of the Interior, to John Barrett, Director General Pan American Union, thanks for the birthday note and his best wishes for future success, 1 typewritten page (6435-av) (Box-folder 9:71)
  - n.d. John Lane (1854-1925) Speech concerning his introduction to the publishing and collecting world as a youth, also mentioning William Thackeray, Charlotte Bronte, and the contemporary English novelist Mr. Locke, 3 typewritten pages on 3 l. (6435) (Box-folder 9:72)
  - [1812] December 19 Mary Elizabeth (Hazlehurst) Latrobe to Dolley Madison, describes her life and that of her husband, the architect Benjamin Latrobe, at Pittsburg, Pennsylvania, where he was building the steamboat Buffalo to ply the Ohio River, mentioning her residence as "one of the best and largest houses in the town, quite new," the beauty of the Monongahela River flowing near her home, the problems with coal dust, the numerous furnaces and foundries in the city, the low cost of living, and other details of early Pittsburg, 4 pages on 1 l., electrostatic copy, original in Dolley Madison Papers (6435) (Box-folder 9:73)
  - 1902 June 25 Fitzhugh Lee (1835-1905) to John Cullen Bryant, writes that he thinks the picture sent to him to be a very good likeness of an unidentified person from one of the latest and best photographs, 1 page (6435) (Box-folder 9:74)
  - 1885 August 6 Fitzhugh Lee (1835-1905) to J[ames] M[cCormick] Dalzell (1838-1924), writes that he is unable to come to the reunion at Caldwell because of his political campaign, 1 page (6435) (Box-folder 9:75)
  - 1926 March 23 Lawrence Lee (1903-1978), editor of Sea Stories and Sport Stories to Atcheson Hench, wishes that he spent more time on pure creation than other things, but "Poetry is simply surging along; and I am almost weary with the constant buzzing of poems, and the continual catching of them." He also expresses appreciation for The Virginia Quarterly Review, 2 pages on 2 l. with envelope (6435-z) (Box-folder 9:76)
  - 1927 January 10 Lawrence Lee (1903-1978), editor of Sea Stories and Sport Stories to Atcheson Hench, asks if any of the students in Hench's writing class have any stories suitable for his magazines and mentions the recent sale of a story by [William] Bruner, 1 typewritten page (6435-z) (Box-folder 9:76)
  - 1928 June 29 Lawrence Lee (1903-1978), editor of Sea Stories and Sport Stories to Atcheson Hench, informs him that someone has requested the address of John R. Phillips, pleases him to help any of the University of Virginia boys interested in a literary career, and speaks of the success of William Bruner, 1 typewritten page with envelope (6435-z) (Box-folder 9:76)
  - 1928 July 10 Lawrence Lee (1903-1978), editor of Sea Stories and Sport Stories to Atcheson Hench, mentions that [John R.] Phillips has settled in, appreciates Hench's kind words about "To a Native State" and suggests "If you see any poetry looking at you from the faces of your classes, please send that person to the hills and rivers, to the apple orchards near Greenwood [Albemarle County, Virginia]" 3 pages on 3 l. with envelope (6435-z) (Box-folder 9:76)
  - 1930 February 24 Lawrence Lee (1903-1978), editor of Sea Stories and Sport Stories to Atcheson Hench, expresses interest in "action fiction with a highly romantic color. We want material which opens with a tense situation and keeps the reader interested by continued developments throughout the manuscript." 1 typewritten page (6435-z) (Box-folder 9:76)
  - 1930 August 12 Lawrence Lee (1903-1978), editor of Sea Stories and Sport Stories to Atcheson Hench, asks for recommendations for a vacancy in his staff in September, 1 typewritten page (6435-z) (Box-folder 9:76)
  - 1930 August 15 Lawrence Lee (1903-1978), editor of Sea Stories and Sport Stories to Atcheson Hench, has heard from Arthur Forester who is interviewing for his position but will consider Frank O. Judy, 1 typewritten page (6435-z) (Box-folder 9:76)
  - 1815 September 2 Richard Henry Lee, Aid-de Camp, Headquarters 2nd [Military Department] to Lt. Edwards, commander of Fort Independence, by order of General [Eleazar Wheelock] Ripley (1782-1839) he is to order a boat manned to carry Lt. Lee to the point, 1 page (6435) (Box-folder 9:77)
  - 1839 December 30 Benjamin Watkins Leigh (1781-1849) to Henry A. Wise (1806-1876) wants to know what Mr. Pickens said about the Harrisburg Convention [1839 Whig National Convention] being a combination of bank influence and Wise's answer to him and plans to "publish a commentary, which will touch his heart and make some impression upon his mind, if his Calhounism has left any capacity in the one for candid reasoning or any room in the other for generous feeling."1 page (6435) (Box-folder 9:78)
  - 1851 October 30 John Letcher (1813-1884) to Henry A. Wise (1806-1876) discusses the court martial of Wise's son and his dismissal from the [Virginia Military Institute] due to his conduct where "he had acted rashly and imprudently but not dishonorably." Letcher also wishes that Wise would visit western Virginia before the election of state officers and supersede Hunter in the Senate, 3 pages on 1 l. (6435) (Box-folder 9:79)
  - 1870 May 13 David Ross Locke [pseudonym Petroleum V. Nasby] (1833-1888) to "My good friend Reid," regrets that he is unable to meet with him this evening having already made an appointment to accompany two Western gentlemen to Wallock Theater, New York, 2 pages on 1 l. (6435) (Box-folder 9:80)
  - 1829 November 30 Marianne Preble Longfellow [Fuller], future wife of Stephen Longfellow whom she divorced around 1850, to her future sister-in-law, Anne Longfellow [Pierce], writes of her misadventures on the way to New York while accompanying her father, William Pitt Preble (1783-1857) to his post as minister to the Netherlands, three page typed transcript with explanatory letter from R.K. Turner, Jr. to Hench, April 4, 1951 (6435) (Box-folder 9:81)
  - n.y. June 29 Pierre Loti [pseudonym of Louis Marie-Julien Viaud], French sailor and writer (1850-1923) to "Cher monsieur," apologizes for sending the proofs late and says "If you can without difficulty send me some of it-you will make me happy; otherwise, I will wait." In French, 2 pages on 1 l. (6435-az) (Box-folder 9:82)
  - 1927-1929 John Livingston Lowes (1867-1945), Harvard University, to Atcheson Hench, thanks him for his note about [Samuel Taylor?] Coleridge's copy of Charles Tennyson's poems coming on the market October 10, 1927; his note about an item in the Anderson Galleries catalog, March 30, 1928; the notice of the Coleridge letters for sale in Heise's catalog, April 23 ,1928; and the Coleridgeana in the Kern sale, January 7, 1929; four typed one page letters (6435) (Box-folder 9:83)
  - 1858 October 12 John Lubbock (1834-1913), 1st Baron Avebury, to P.O'Callaghan, advises O'Callaghan on how not to be elected to the Athenaeum Club, 2 pages on 1 l. (6435-a) (Box-folder 9:84)
  - 1862 August 25 Miles Daniel McAlester (1832-1869), Yorktown, Virginia, Lt. of Engineers, to General Erasmus Darwin Keyes (1810-1895), writes concerning the number of men and details of arranging work parties for tomorrow, 2 pages on 1 l. (6435) (Box-folder 9:85)
  - 1877 July 9 W. Gordon McCabe (1841-1920) to John Esten Cooke (1830-1886), has not received the book sent to him but would love to do a literary notice of the novel for the Petersburg Post when it arrives and hopes that Cooke saw his address "The Defense of Petersburg" four pages on 1 l. (6435) (Box-folder 9:86)
  - 1787 October 31 Henry McKenzie (1745-1831) to Mr. [Thomas?] Cadell, Bookseller, Strand, London, asks how his paper The Lounger was doing as "I see it pillaged liberally in various magazines, etc. which I reckon a good sign." He also mentions the poems of Hamilton of Bonjour, 2 pages on 1 l. (6435-a) (Box-folder 9:87)
  - 1933-1950 Folger McKinsey's Recollections of Walt Whitman from his column in The Baltimore Sun; also his obituary, printed news clippings (6435-c) (Box-folder 9:88)
  - 1894 August 8 Katharine Sarah Gadsden Macquoid (1824-1917) to Messrs. Roberts Brothers, has asked Messrs. Harper to send them a two volume typescript copy of her book Dolly's Grandfathers, to be published in England in 1895, for possible publication in America; and wishes to hear their terms for American right of issue, 2 pages on 1 l. (6435-a) (Box-folder 9:89)
  - 1897 October 6 Jules Massanet (1842-1912) to unidentified male correspondent, possibly a singer, thanks him for his excellent letter, in French, electrostatic copy, original in Vault-Autograph File, 1 page (6435-j) (Box-folder 9:90)
  - n.d. Jules Massanet (1842-1912) Untitled Music Manuscripts, electrostatic copies, original in Vault-Autograph File, 3 items (6435-aw) (Box-folder 9:91)
  - 1920 April 26 M. Massenet to "Cher confrere" congratulations on a very picturesque title [Estrangete'?], in French, 2 pages on 1 l. (6435-l) (Box-folder 9:92)
  - [post 1859] Tuesday Gerald Massey (1828-1907) to Messrs. Osgood & Co., sends a new financial proposal for the publisher to issue a new collection in one volume before the end of April for $250 dollars down for past sales and the present matter and then "fine" him "ten per cent interim on the new venture payable annually", 4 pages on 1 l. (6435-a) (Box-folder 9:93)
  - ca. 1858-1859 Gerald Massey (1828-1907) to "My dear Fields," hopes the sale of his book will prove remunerative to the firm, asks him to forward any reviews worth reading, presses him to visit them in the Lake District where they have a large house not much furnished, and advises him to take the L & N Western Rail via Carnforth, 4 pages on 1 l. (6435-a) (Box-folder 9:94)
  - [ca. 1873] July 4 Gerald Massey (1828-1907) to "My dear Fields," tells him he is coming to lecture in America and asks him to help publicize the lectures in the Boston papers, sending him "a little autograph letter of Tennyson's as a bribe" and inquiring about Bayard Taylor, 2 pages on 1 l., possibly a copy in another hand (6435-a) (Box-folder 9:95)
  - 1878 May 15 Dabney Herndon Maury (1822-1900) to Judge Jeremiah Black (1810-1883), Maury sends a copy of his article "Grant as a Soldier and as a Civilian" and repeats his request for Black to write for or speak before the Southern Historical Society, 2 pages on 1 l. (6435-j) (Box-folder 9:96)
  - 1873 January 8 Dabney Herndon Maury (1822-1900) to J.J. Hopkins, Secretary of the Piedmont & Arlington Life Insurance Company, asks him to send directly to John L. Ross the same blank notes that were sent to Maury in the case of Mr. Lampkin, with all necessary instructions and explanations, and expresses concern over the business situation in New Orleans, 1 page (6435) (Box-folder 9:97)
  - 1890 January 28 Dabney Herndon Maury (1822-1900) to "Dear Sir," sends his autograph with pleasure, 1 page (6435) (Box-folder 9:98)
  - 1859 January 19 Matthew Fontaine Maury (1806-1873) to James H. Armsby (1809-1875), Secretary of the Board of Trustees Dudley Observatory, Albany, New York, accepts his invitation to visit the Dudley Observatory and to meet its new director, Professor [Ormsby MacKnight] Mitchel, health permitting, 2 pages on 1 l. (6435) (Box-folder 9:99)
  - 1858 September 13 Matthew Fontaine Maury (1806-1873) to Messrs. Bond & Son, reports on the success and failure of various chronometers placed at the Observatory in Washington during the trial period which had begun about a year ago and had expired. William Cranch Bond (1789-1859) was the first director of the Harvard College Observatory and owner of an instrument supply firm in Boston, 2 pages on 1 l. (6435) (Box-folder 9:100)
  - 1841 October 4 Matthew Fontaine Maury (1806-1873) to Chief Clerk of the Navy, John D. Simms, recommending John M. Maury, son of R.B. Maury, for a midshipman appointment (6435) (Box-folder 9:101)
  - 1870 June 23 William Holmes McGuffey (1800-1873) to C.H. Winston, unable to provide a paper as he wished due to his busy schedule at the University of Virginia, 1 page (6435) (Box-folder 9:102)
  - [1823?] March 13 William Charles Macready (1793-1873), actor in the title role of Mitford's play Julian which was produced at Covent Garden in 1823, to Mary Russell Mitford (1787-1855), discusses his attempts to have her play published and his honor at being an actor in her play, Julian, 3 pages on 1 l. (6435-a) (Box-folder 9:103)
  - 1854 January 26 R[ichard] K[idder] Meade (1803-1862), Petersburg, Virginia, to Colonel Samuel Pickens, Greensboro, Alabama, discusses the possible sale of his land in [Alabama?] to Pickens and other business matters, 2 pages on 1 l. (6435) (Box-folder 10:1)
  - 1771 December 31 James Mercer (1736-1793) to Robert Carter, Williamsburg, Virginia, discusses business matters, mentioning an agreement uniting the Grand Company and the Ohio Company with his consent, with typed transcript, 3 pages on 1 l. (6435-ai) (Box-folder 10:2)
  - 1910 Joaquin Miller (1839-1913) Autograph on a Postcard of his home (6435) (Box-folder 10:3)
  - [ca. 1850] Mary Russell Mitford (1787-1855) to "My dear friend," [William Cox Bennett (1820-1895)] writes concerning her friend, Henry Chorley as an example of "how much danger there is ever to talent in an exclusive life of literature. My friend Henry Chorley for instance - just read his play, & you will see how much a really fine genius has been injured by the habit of day to day writing upon all works of subjects - how much the talent is frittered away by the weekly demands of the Atheneum. The play has much that is excellent - but wants depth, breadth, motive - in fact the concentrated attention which you give to your charming lyrics because you bring to them a power unwasted by [?] in literature." She also writes about a little volume by John Hughes (1790-1857), friend of Robert Southey and Sir Walter Scott, called Lays of Past Days published in 1850 and "dedicated to your unworthy servant" and goes on at length to discuss his work and talents, "In short it is a piece of ill luck that he happens to be a man of fortune or he would have been a very eminent artist of some sort or other" 4 pages on 1 l., with typed transcript (6435-a) (Box-folder 10:4)
  - 1851 August 12 Mary Russell Mitford (1787-1855) to William Cox Bennett (1820-1895), writes "I think the enclosed [bit] will about complete my three [volumes] - rather more than less - If not more extracts can be easily added - I mean that there are two or three other articles which I have fairly cut off from my original scheme which might be added to this [Recollections of A Literary Life?]." She also asks to borrow a few books and complains that "Mr. [Henry F.?] Chorley never kept either the M.S.S. or the proofs of the bits he cut out to fit into his journal so that what I have to do to make the matter out is more troublesome than can be thought." Mitford mentions recovering her copy of Daniel Webster's speeches after a few years absence and her plans to make it her newest short interesting article. 4 pages on 1 l., with envelope and typed transcript (6435-a) (Box-folder 10:4)
  - [ca. 1852?] Mary Russell Mitford (1787-1855) to William Cox Bennett (1820-1895), thanks him for his help in coming to an agreement for the title of her book, possibly her Recollections of a Literary Life Books, Places and People (first published in 1852), as "Mr. Hughes says that Bentley is a terrible bully" although she still liked her title the best; mentions her [Dorrington?] article, Mr. Kingsley who is "better in books than conversation," and a distant cousin who was canon of Westminster, inheriting [Brownhill?] from old Sir John; 4 pages on 1 l. with typed transcript (6435-a) (Box-folder 10:4)
  - 1854 July 4 Mary Russell Mitford (1787-1855) to William Cox Bennett (1820-1895), asks if he has seen a very favorable review of Atherton and Other Tales in the New Quarterly and rejoices that Mrs. [Emma?] Bennett is safe, 2 pages on 1 l., with envelope and typed transcript (6435-a) (Box-folder 10:4)
  - [post 1846] Mary Russell Mitford (1787-1855) to William Cox Bennett (1820-1895), writes about a "charming young poetess" visiting with her, the volume of her "ballads are chiefly on very graphic and picturesque bits of history told with both plainness & a spirit that I greatly like - you may see some of them in Jerrold's Magazine. She, who is charmed with some of your lyrics, has taken charge of a copy of Baby May" and other titles by Bennett to deliver to Lord Nugent, "It is a great thing to secure a man of his taste & influence - the great point being to show such people only the best - never to let them see in a [detached way?] any but the very best; hopes to bring some of her friend's poems to her majesty's notice, "though I don't believe the Queen ever reads verses by anybody - I know that she had never read a line of Wordsworth's when he was invited to the Palace"; mentions a visit from James Cobbett; and tells of being notified of honorary membership in the Whittington Club (instituted under the auspices of Douglas Jerrold in 1846), 4 pages on 1 l. with typed transcript (6435-a) (Box-folder 10:4)
  - [ca. 1850 December] Mary Russell Mitford (1787-1855) to "My dear friend" [probably William Cox Bennett (1820-1895)], tells him that she has written to Mrs. Acton Tindal [Henrietta Euphemia Harrison Tindal (d. 1879)] poet and novelist "that you will send her your book [Poems] through Chapman and Hall your mutual publishers." Chapman and Hall published Tindal's Lines and Leaves also in 1850. She also describes a packet she received from America containing Songs of Labor by John Whittier, and "Astraea" by Oliver Wendell Holmes (which he read to the Phi Beta Kappa Society of Yale College in 1850). She also rejoices to hear what Chapman says [about his work?], "I can't help thinking that the success will come sooner than I expected - that it will come seems to me certain." She also has had a letter from Henry Chorley, "talking as he always does about his hard work & his sorrows & about putting in articles after [Christmas?]" with the Lady's Companion progressing slowly. 4 pages on 1 l. with typed transcript (6435-a) (Box-folder 10:5)
  - [1852 January] Mary Russell Mitford (1787-1855) to "My dear friend" [probably William Cox Bennett (1820-1895)] mentions several acquaintances and writers, including a letter from a Dublin barrister, Mr. [Digby] Starkey, a poet and "a first rate man in every way" who quoted another poet, Mr. Prince (said to be a Lancashire weaver), in his letter creating her interest in getting his volume of poetry, Mr. Barnes, a Dorsetshire poet, and dear Mr. Fields whose address she lacks. She also writes about pregnant Mrs. Warburton, who still clings to the hope that her husband was saved by a passing boat and whose first grief was so intense they feared for her life. Eliot Warburton (1810-1852), an Irish traveler and novelist, was aboard the steamship RMS Amazon when it sank on January 4, 1852. She also mentions the trouncing that the Times received from everyone, "above all when dear old Joseph [Hume?] put the coping stone on the rebuke by saying that he hoped Louis Napoleon as a man of sense would recollect that journalism was a trade like any other trade - they do it merely for base [?] - a cry - like the Protestant bigotry of last year." 4 pages on 1 l., with typed transcript (6435-a) (Box-folder 10:5)
  - n.d. Mary Russell Mitford (1787-1855) to Mr. Langford, thanks him for his kindness in making her acquaintance and hope to entice him to return during the season of roses and strawberries, 2 pages on 1 l. with typed transcript (6435-a) (Box-folder 10:6)
  - 1854 September 27 Mary Russell Mitford (1787-1855) to [Frances] Trollope (1780-1863), rejoices to hear from her old friend, refers to Elizabeth Barrett Browning who could tell Trollope more of her condition, "a story of suffering" due to a bad fall from her pony chaise in Swallowfield Park which injured her spine leaving her unable to move from her chair without severe pain. Due to the work of her physician, she has improved some and is astonished at the kindness of her friends and neighbors in her extremity, 4 pages on 1 l., with envelope fragment and typed transcript (6435-a) (Box-folder 10:7)
  - 1828 [March 1] Mary Russell Mitford (1787-1855) to Mrs. Watts, promises to do all she can for her little book, but she is in the midst of getting out a little book of her own; plans to take care of Mr. Watts souvenir as soon as possible; and writes "Mr. Kemble says that as far as any manager can ever answer for the production of a play he intends to bring out mine after Easter" and mentions Mrs. B. Hofland, a children's author, 3 pages on 1 l., with engraving of Mitford and typed transcript (6435-a) (Box-folder 10:8)
  - 1920 November 26 Harriet Monroe (1860-1936) to Ruth Shepard Phelps [Morand] (1876-1949), thanks her for the "charming old buckles" which arrived all right, written on a Poetry A Magazine of Verse postcard (6435-aj) (Box-folder 10:9)
  - n.d. [James Monroe] Manuscript Fragment concerning the acquisition of Florida, 2 p. on 1 l., copy, original in Vault- Monroe (6435) (Box-folder 10:10)
  - 1825 J[?] 15 James Montgomery (1771-1854) to "Dear Sir" thanks him for the musical compositions incorporating his words of verse "set to your delightful strains" asks that he send them folded flat to Messrs. Longman & Co., 1 page (6435-a) (Box-folder 10:11)
  - 1850 October 25 Nathaniel Fish Moore (1782-1872) to an unidentified correspondent, recommends [George Christian] Shaeffer for the Chair of Chemistry at William and Mary College, Williamsburg, Virginia, 2 pages on 1 l. (6435-aj) (Box-folder 10:12)
  - 1861 September 13 Samuel McDowell Moore (1796-1875), Lexington, Virginia, to Governor John Letcher (1813-1884), having recently returned from General Lee's encampment in the northwest, he warns that the condition of the road leading to the Milboro Depot by Warm Springs and Huntersville is in very poor condition with mud one to two foot deep which will make it almost impossible to transport provisions for the army in wagons and volunteers to supervise the repair of the road if given enough slave labor and supplies, 3 pages on 1 l. (6435) (Box-folder 10:13)